[Music]
if the current operating system for
society is failing what could an
alternative look like in 2013
Jim rut the former chairman of the world
renowned SantaFe Institute
brought together a group of renegade
thinkers for a series of meetings in
Staunton Virginia to try to answer that
question the team ranged from complexity
theorists to culture hackers and
evolutionary biologists all united by a
conviction that the current system was
unsustainable and probably self
terminating when I arrived at the
Stanton meetings the framing surrounded
the shared recognition and I think
characterized everybody in the room that
civilization was on a dangerous track
some of us believed the track to be
fatal in the near term initially the
plan was to create a new political party
the Emancipation Party overtime that
shifted on to a different project how to
change the culture it gained a title
game B why do you think that name
particularly stuck if you're unhappy
with the status quo then game B has to
be what the status quo isn't so better
the devil I don't know than the devil I
know but in 2014 the project stalled Jim
rut said it went into spore mode
recently some of these spores have
germinated with a new surge of interest
in game B so what can be learned from
what happened to the original project
love if you could tell the story like
fairly concisely but the story of game B
from the Emancipation Party to the
meeting that Staunton just a sort of
broad overview and they'll dip will kind
of delve down into the details of it all
right it goes back a little further to a
document I wrote in I got published at
April 2012 and I invited some people to
read it and critique it and develop some
momentum and resulted in a meeting in
Stanton Virginia in September 2012 where
were you know seven or eight people said
what are we going to do you know the
world needs changing my document was
most
about a new monetary system but also
included a new financial system some
ideas about new political systems etc
and we decided for better for worse to
start a new political party right we
didn't know dick about political parties
and we decided we'd start one anyway and
we started having we were strong
believers that face-to-face was where
real stuff happened
I've long expressed the doctrine that
there's a distinction between weak links
and strong links weak links is mostly
what you get online though sometimes you
get strong links from online and strong
links are mostly what you get
face-to-face so you can get weak links
face-to-face too but anyway we decided
to meet regularly every six to eight
weeks to do whatever it was we're gonna
do and they became a series of meetings
known as Stanton one through five and so
the first one we decide we're gonna
launch a party I don't know if we came
up with the name at that point but
somewhere soon thereafter we came up
with the name emancipation party we
created a series of reforms and we
decided that we were going to call for a
debt Jubilee interesting all that stuff
at least the later version of it the
January 2013 version of it still up on
the Emancipation Party dot-org website
if anybody is interested in looking at
it so anyway I think in late November
early December we launched the party out
marketed at the people we knew and what
arrogant we were incompetent fairly
quickly we got a couple hundred people
to join and we decided to make it like a
19th century European party where you
had to pay dues twenty dollars a month
and what we also allow people to
optionally select I can't afford 20 I'll
pay five as part of the model to avoid
having to depend on fundraising and
money bags right and so we quickly
raised a couple of got a couple hundred
people and then then in January we took
stock of where we were and we said mmm
we did pretty good with baby boomers
good enough that from an early test
marketing perspective it would say
proceed with Gen Xers we did not half as
well as we did with boomers which from
our marketing experience would have said
probably improvable by fine-tuning a
were a period of time to make it good
enough to launch and you often find you
know version 0.8 the the early marketing
doesn't quite make sense but it's close
enough that you believe you can tweak it
over a few months and he had to make
sense millennial Millennials there
weren't Z's yet Millennials were a
complete washout we did not get a single
millennial to join not one and we went
back and talked to some Millennials and
it was quite uniform that the idea of a
political party was anathema It was as
if you'd said catch it right
Emancipation Party catch it and even
though the reforms as you'll see are
very progressive and millennial friendly
things like what we'd now call Medicare
for all ubi ending the drug wars you
know radical transparency and finance a
whole bunch of cool new ideas you'd
think Millennials would like at least
progressive ones the idea of calling it
a political party was horrible and
asking for their subscription was also
horrible they assumed it had to be a
scam they couldn't figure out what scam
it was they figured it had to be a scam
so anyway we said shit launching a party
to just appeal to Millennials to boomers
not a good idea the future is young
people and if this thing won't appeal to
Millennials then we should not proceed
so we basically stopped the limited
marketing the test marketing we were
doing and said let's rethink what we're
doing and how to do it better and or how
to restructure to respect or promote it
or rebrand it or something to appeal to
Millennials and it was at that point in
a meeting Stanton 3 in January 2013 that
Jordan Greenhalgh at the time now known
as Jordan Hall went to the whiteboard
and start drawing a picture and
essentially he drew a fairly steep cone
or pyramid or something triangle
probably as the Emancipation Party and
then he drew broad Ram
leading up to it and he said what we
really need is a softer less
well-defined social movement that
articulates some or many of the values
of the Emancipation Party but is not
positioned as a political party and
requires no contributions and requires
no commitment to any action per se and
it will be a gradual on-ramp that'll
eventually that will particularly design
to appeal to Millennials and will
eventually get some of them at least
ready to join the emancipation party and
that what I would say was the mental
model of what eventually became game
being that it was social movement that
incorporated value a set of values but
wasn't you know strictly defined and
would appeal to young people but would
gradually move them along eventually
become ready for to be more politically
active and then we serve that all wild
conversation for a goodly part of the
rest of that meeting about well what
would this thing be right we came up
with some I believe we came up with some
principles of that meeting which would
include that it be non hierarchical that
that would be a fundamental value that
it would be network centric and that we
that it needed to eventually lead to a
social operating system that had
long-term metastability that it could
list exists for centuries at least and
interestingly all three of those things
to this day I believe are fundamental
values in in neo game be thinking and it
was quite interesting you know and very
rapidly became clear that the interest
of at least a majority of the
participants in this activity which of
that point is probably 25 or 30 people
more of them were interested in this
social movement and were interested in
the party but interested in the party
continued you know through the rest at
least until September 2013 but very
clear that this concept of this vague
social movement is where the energy
started to be
and it may well have been in one of
those conversations that that at that
time that the concept in a generic sense
not a branded sense is that game a is
the status quo and game B is this new
social movement social operating system
and you sort of lack of a better term
essentially and that we would position
game B as you know something that the
world would eventually transition to and
the game B was explicitly parasitize a
to accelerate there's certainly a fair
amount of acceleration ism in that early
talking and then the that meeting ended
and the meetings ran from Friday evening
where we started with the dinner to a
full long intense day on Saturday and
then a half a day on Sunday that was
mostly synthesis of what we had cooked
on Saturday and so we went home with
this new concept in the air and we
continued to communicate as we always
did on Basecamp Basecamp went all the
way back to September 2012 and was the
main online community for you know the
inner circle of the emancipation party
and then what became game B and we
shattered away as we always did you know
I was telling David there's probably at
least 10,000 posts on basically it might
be a hundred thousand it's a whole bunch
we shattered away way way too much
probably and during this time this vague
idea started getting some legs on it and
that stanton for which happened in April
2013 Jordan Hall Jordan green Hall at
that point now Hall made it gave a
presentation which don't believe he was
still yet calling it game B but it was
very much much more meat on the bones of
what we now call game B and I also had
developed a lot of support and you know
etc at the same time or soon thereafter
I'm going to look at the timeline Thor
Muller made the explicit suggestion that
we brand the whole effort game B earlier
game B had been sort of a generic
comparison of
where we're from game a to where we're
going game B but it was thought to be
just a you know a talking point internal
generic and not for brand and Thor was
the one I believe who decided that it
should be branded a game be proposed
that and there was some discussion as
there always wasn't everything had to do
with with the community and but it fixed
pretty quickly that people said okay
let's go with that and then from that
point forward through May and June we
started to ramp up the community mostly
focused on game B almost all the new
people that came in to the inner
community were more interested in game B
than they were in the emancipation party
though there were still a dozen or so
stalwarts including me still interested
principally in the party and the event
and then the base camp site kept getting
busier and busier and busier and then
some fissures started to appear in the
community which are saying oh if we want
to talk about that separately but maybe
we should so the only fissure started to
appear conflict different views strongly
felt ugly fights and over that summer
essentially the the community as a
intense operating entity started unwind
the last stanton meeting was stanton v
in june of 2013 we had said there be a
stand 6 in august it never happened you
know we tried some other pivots but and
then I I think probably in January 2014
declared the thing to be done and I
think I use the words it's time for us
to go into spore mode where we've all
learned a lot from each other and have
co-created a whole bunch of things even
if we don't agree with them all agree
with each other about everything so it
is now time for us to go back into the
world live our lives do our thinking and
some of this will probably continue
working on game B ish things or not and
perhaps in the future game B will come
back to
and interestingly I don't know in the
last three four or five months game B
has come back to life very I mean I
thought it was a I didn't know what I
don't know I knew it was possible but if
you'd asked me in January 2014 what's
the chances I would have said less than
50/50 probably but way higher than zero
and for some reason it started to
rebuttal pretty substantially and
interesting a lot of it independent of
the original game B people over on
Twitter if you want to see what they've
been up to search on hash check hash tag
game B or just game B by itself and
you'll find all kinds of people that
nobody in the you know the stanton
meetings community had ever ever known
know they and I think they're a lot of
more driven by listening to podcasts and
reading documents and stuff so that's in
a very short mostly short form of the
history of game B though I should say
that Jordan now Hall has continued to
work game B in fact he asked me at the
time we went to sport mode what should
he work on and I told him deep code
which was a name he may have come up
with but was the idea of thinking as
deeply as you can about the
philosophical principles of what we're
doing and you know he's continued to
publish under the name deep code on
medium and has written a lot of really
good things he then later met two people
out where he lives in Southern
California Daniel Sherman burger and
Forrest Landry and the three of them
have done some very good work and they
explicitly branded it game B and have
been on lots of podcasts have written
some documents and blog posts etc some
medium posts which I call this the San
Diego interpretation of game B and it is
and while it's the one that's furthest
along I think it's important for people
to know that it is not the definitive
game B and they would be the first to
admit that game B is still very
undercooked and under defined but they
have put some stakes in the ground and I
think they're very useful bits of work
that they've done and I would
people that are interested in learning
more about the current thinking of
Gambia to look at the San Diego
interpretation but realize that it's one
interpretation along as many and by no
means fully defines what game B could or
should be what was the initial frame
able to hold into price when he first
came into it so when I arrived at the
Stanton meetings the framing surrounded
the shared recognition and I think
characterized everybody in the room that
civilization was on a dangerous track
some of us believed the track to be
fatal in the near term and the question
was could we figure out some alternative
trajectory that was not only better but
that was accessible from where we were
at that time in history which would have
been about 2013 and do you think
everyone who was part of the initial
project recognized those sort of stakes
or recognized it as that kind of
civilization the important project I
think the degree of recognition varied a
lot I think everybody recognized that
there was something concerning about the
way civilization presently runs and
maybe everybody in the room would
recognize that it was dangerous but the
necessity to do something was a subset
of us recognized the urgency of it and
what was achieved like in the first in
the first few meetings what did he feel
was achieved well I think all of these
kinds of projects have the same initial
trajectory which is you have to teach
each other to speak your language to see
things that are particularly clear from
your vantage point and you have to let
them do the same and if that fails then
you don't have a project and if that
succeeds then you can begin to build on
the shared understanding there's no way
to skip that phase and so unfortunately
we didn't have enough time together to
get much past it but I think we did a
lot of work building a shared
understanding
and figuring out what direction that we
would need the head and the name game be
is that a reference to sort of game
theory and game a beings the kind of
civilization we have at the moment game
B being sort of placeholder for
something new was was the name chosen
because it represented kind of the game
theoretic constraints of kind of a
civilization as it is well I can't say
why the name was chosen I became aware
of it Jordan gave a presentation at the
board and it roughly laid out that we
live in something that we would loosely
call game a and that we needed to go
somewhere called game B and basically
the idea was there was so little content
in that name that it could work almost
no matter what our priors were about the
situation we live in and the fact that
we needed to do something new I do think
whether it was intentionally a reference
to game theory or not a an effort to
figure out how civilization functions
and what alternative might exist
ultimately comes down to your ability to
take away all of the layers of meaning
that we impose on our system to
understand how it does function which
would inherently be analogous to some
sort of game and that a system that we
arrived at would also inevitably even
fit into the same rubric so really maybe
that name is just evidence of our shared
understanding that there was a project
and its basic nature would be to look at
the rules of our current system and to
rework them in such a way that our
system would function better and how
would you summarize that for you what at
what are the failure conditions of game
a versus what what does game a need to
be well game xre what does game B need
to be well you know I was brought in
because there was an awareness that
there was something evolutionary about
the whole question and that they needed
someone to speak to it rather directly
and the way I would phrase the problem
is this we have a tendency as humans
problems and we solved them at all sorts
of different scales whether it's little
inventions that reduce the amount of
work involved in some sort of objective
or whether we are architecting cities or
civilizations or whatever what have you
and the problem is that when we build
these things in large measure because
our history of building such things is
pre-darwinian we are not aware that we
are building an entity that will evolve
according to whatever niche space it
finds itself in and so if you look at
for example the American experiment the
American experiment was architected by
highly intelligent people who understood
more or less what their objectives were
but they were prior to the Origin of
Species and so they did not recognize
that in constructing this entity they
were also building something that would
morph and whatever their intentions had
been at first would be inevitably
swallowed by the system of incentives
that surrounded the project and that
ultimately we would find out what that
niche space looked like because the
entity they were building would explore
it so I think we've done this time and
time again we've done it politically
we've done it economically where we've
set up a system we've said what we
wanted and then we discover over time
that it turns into something we didn't
anticipate so my contribution to game be
in part was to recognize that this was
an evolutionary space and it would
therefore either fall victim to
evolutionary forces that it was unaware
of or take advantage of evolutionary
forces that it could be made aware of
why do you think that name particularly
stuck again as I said earlier if you're
unhappy with the status quo then game B
has to be what the status quo isn't so
better the devil I don't know than the
devil I know and what was the need for
the Emancipation Party and then game B
how would you sort of summarize that
because daniel trachtenberg ER for
example talks about a kind of self
terminating system and do you do you
agree with that or what would you how we
frame the need for the whole movement I
would say the Emancipation Party
was let was not that way really we
thought that the political and economic
systems could collapse from their own
internal contradictions but we were not
yet focused on bigger questions about
that our is our social operating system
literally and heading for suicide I
would say those conversations became
part of the discussion in the game be
world though probably weren't dominant
in the dominant sense well and it was
that the world was not good not say
particularly the Western world was not
good and in fact one of the I think more
succinct statements about game B was the
purpose of game B is to create a society
we'd actually like to live in and would
be proud to leave to our children and we
would say we did not believe that game a
that either of those criteria so it's
really more of it more driven by the
fact that we did not think the current
game a produced the best life for people
yeah who came up with the name game B
that's an interesting question as I said
earlier I actually found on Basecamp
that Thor was the first to propose it as
the branded name of the movement so it's
at one level to say that the person who
said we should call what we're doing
game B is Thor Mahler however it's quite
possible if I'm pretty sure it was that
the terms game a and game B is just
generics to differentiate between the
status quo and the whatever's coming
next
almost certainly we're floating around
in fact we're certainly floating around
in the conversation prior to that so who
said the word game B first I don't know
could well have been Jordan at least one
person thinks it was Brett Weinstein
Stein could have been Thor but not sure
but I would give Thor the nod of
proposing it as the brand and what were
the specifics that were talks about at
the meetings what what sort of
because game be as you said it's like a
placeholder it it doesn't actually mean
it just means an alternative to game a
so what were the sort of solid ideas
that were being shared at the meetings
that have a long long long lists of them
which would come and they would go
unlike the Emancipation Party was a very
discipline that worked up to ten
carefully defined reforms which are
written about exhaustively on the
website game B was much more amorphous
and ideas came and ideas went but I said
the the core three or non-hierarchical
was very strongly a value that
traditional top-down command control
organizations were not about what game B
is in fact I would say that in neo game
B terms that has been resurrected in a
stronger form which is Jordan likes to
say game B will not manage the complex
via the complicated complicated meaning
things with many highly defined moving
parts like a corporation
the second was net-centric that again
fits closely with non hierarchical that
there would be essentially fractal scale
of organization and people inter
communicating with each other as peers
in fact this is very something something
that unfortunately has not come back in
Neo game B and we had the name Pierre is
what we called each other we were all
peers kind of like comrade right so you
were a game B Pierre if you were a
member of the interest you know the
Facebook or the Basecamp inner circle we
talked about self actualization and from
Maslow's hierarchy as one of the pole
stars for what a good society was what
is a society that would we'd like to
live in and leave to our children is a
society where self-actualization is the
highest value not he who dies with the
most toys wins where some of the
fracture starting to come in in game B
was there was one sub faction that
believed changing yourself first was
primary and then there was another
faction that believed that
creating new institutions like a better
monetary system better sense making
capabilities permaculture for food
cohousing
was cohousing was definitely something
people were interested in as a piece
part towards game B so the building the
piece parts and the institutions versus
changing as a person where it was a a
fission that started to become clear in
May and actually grew and grew and grew
until it eventually was probably the
main fission that caused the community
to kind of set upon itself in a not too
pleasant way and so there were people
working on the what does it mean to
change your self direction and then
there were people thinking about these
various piece parts and many of them by
this point not the party anymore but
again things like cohousing permaculture
etc or minor monetary systems
independent of a political party so what
I understand there were five meetings at
stanton and there was a six that was
planned but it never went ahead because
the sense was that there wasn't enough
alignment among the people who are going
to be there to make it worthwhile
what was your experience at that time
what what did he feel happened well in
some sense I don't know why we ever
expected anything different to occur so
I don't even take it as evidence that we
did something wrong that game B came
apart what I think is true is that if
you are embarking on a project as
ambitious as we were then you should
expect to fail many many times and each
of those times it is incumbent on you to
figure out what went wrong and to reduce
or eliminate the chances of that same
failure happening again
it's a classic question of prototyping
and in this case we were prototyping two
things we were trying to design a set of
rules for civilization that might work
going forward but we also needed to
design a set of rules for how we would
interact over this question that would
work and it was that second thing that
came apart on us
I was hard on the game B community after
it came apart because I thought it did
not do a great job in fact it really
didn't do any job of analyzing the
particular breakdown so that or their a
game C games he could profit from the
knowledge of what had happened to game B
and maybe we'd get to you know game
LMNOP who knows before we would actually
figure out how to do it right but that
would be an absolutely worthy investment
what happened is we left the space in a
situation where it was as likely to
suffer the same failure as a new one and
that meant that we weren't likely to
make progress we were basically in
evolutionary terms waiting for a hopeful
monster rather than learning from our
mistakes so what do you think of the key
lessons or the key realizations that you
think are really important to know well
I have a overarching one which is quite
live for me at the moment because I'm
watching the game be space come into
public consciousness and I feel like
there is an error and there's some
awareness of this although I don't think
the awareness is what it needs to be
there is some danger of imagining that
game B is or could be an organization or
a plan for civilization going forward I
don't think it can be and I think any
attempt to make it either of those
things is going to result in at best a
simple failure and at worst something
potentially monstrous so what I'd like
to see is the recognition that game B is
actually fairly easy to define it is the
virtue of it is that it is not a highly
elaborate description of anything it is
a very basic sketch of something and
that what that sketch ought to do is it
ought to set in motion many projects
once people understand what it is that
needs to be achieved in order to save
humanity from the trajectory that it's
currently on then in principle anybody
attempt to describe some mechanism that
moves in the direction of game B and I
would point out that this doesn't have
to be at the scale of civilization
really we have dozens of problems in
society we have problems with healthcare
we have problems with education we have
problems in our courts we have problems
with homelessness and everything else
and what I would like to see in addition
to a large number of groups tackle the
question of what a game B might look
like across civilization I would also
like to see people tackling the question
of well what is the game B solution for
let's say City Planning and traffic what
is the game B solution for medical care
all of these things each of them is ripe
for its own game B solution and if you
for example came up with game B for
education which is a project I'm
actually working on with Heather that
that would in and of itself be a major
contribution and if you solved something
if you came up with game B for education
that obviously becomes fertile ground it
becomes a place to discuss the larger
question of civilization so game B is a
a set of parameters that describes a
superior future state and it can exist
at all scales in other words if you had
an overarching game be it would be
composed of lots of little game B's so
I'd like to see the space recognize that
the thing to do is not to gather around
game B itself and figure out you know
who the voices of game B are the thing
to do is to recognize that game B is a
statement about a design space and then
for people to create initiatives that
function inside that design space and
attempt to produce either a viable
something-or-other or a kind of
knowledge about what doesn't work and
why and you mentioned that there's a
basic sketch of what the game B space
needs to look like you want to sketch
that out for us sure well the first
recognition about game B is that it has
to be competitively superior to our
system and this is a difficult thing to
swallow once you recognize that even if
you described a wonderful future state
that would be terrific for people and
you presented it
there is no pathway for it to find its
way into the structures that make up
civilization in other words the
description is not sufficient
what's worse if you turn it over to
democracy and you allow us to try to
vote it into place it will be so
butchered along the way by people who
have their personal reasons to get in
the road that it will be unrecognizable
and almost certainly again either a
failure or worse by the time it makes it
into structural space what we need to do
is you mean to look for something that
has the characteristics of the
smartphone right so the smartphone took
over civilization not because anybody
told us you have to have a smartphone
but because for each of us there were
reasons that we wanted it it enhanced
our lives and to take two obvious
examples the smartphone camera is now
the most popular camera on earth by
orders of magnitude and it is actually
making photography into a much more
widespread
I hesitate to even call it a hobby
something almost all of us do some
fraction of the time and so the ability
to have a highly capable camera and
what's more even a video camera in your
pocket it just changes the way we live
it means that really at any moment that
I want you to see what I'm seeing I can
capture it and I can send it to you
instantly really so that's a remarkable
capacity likewise the ability to drop
into almost any city on earth and find a
location that I want to be and dead
reckon my way there with the help of
a navigation device these are
spectacular characteristics so those
sorts of things caused us all to embrace
this technology now unfortunately the
underlying businesses that make the
phone and that populate it with apps
those businesses are overwhelmingly
gamei entities and so unfortunately it's
a Faustian bargain in this device that
makes us so marvelously capable is now
hell-bent on addicting us to
counterproductive behaviors and
everything else so it's not as if the
cellphone is a game B device but what it
is is a demonstration then if something
empowers you enough people will embrace
it without having to be told that they
need to embrace it or without anybody
being without anybody voting it into
into existence it just simply takes over
by virtue of competitive superiority so
characteristic one of game B is that it
is competitively superior so that people
will embrace it not because we tell them
to but because they know it's good for
them to to participate something like
that can sweep over civilization
relatively easily the second
characteristic is really it comes in two
forms
the structure has to at least be robust
and maybe at first that's all it could
be but ultimately the game B structure
has to be anti fragile that is to say
that challenge causes it to become
stronger rather than weaker and this is
a characteristic of most evolutionary
systems so it has to have that
characteristic or it won't persist
through its early phases ultimately it
has to be what we would call an
evolutionarily stable strategy an
evolutionarily stable strategy is a
strategy that is not displace about by
alternatives so in other words if some
parasitic strategy or some competitive
strategy emerges and Challen
is a game be structure the game be
structure has to be robust and it has to
to defeat it so this is an analog of the
competitive ability to sweep
civilization and the ability to remain
in place those two things go together
and in the last set of characteristics
have to do with what game be what
achieve and I would claim that there are
a set of values that almost any person
who is not authoritarian minded would
agree are highly desirable in in a
society so things like fairness security
protection from catastrophic risk these
sorts of things are relatively easy to
get people to agree to and I've tried
this experiment many times I've asked
rooms full of people I don't know how
they feel about these things and what
she discovers that we all really agree
on the list of things that civilization
should accomplish what we disagree over
is an analysis of where we stand in that
project how good our society is at for
example giving people fair access to the
market and we disagree on the priority
the ordering of these things that we
would dictate in other words some people
would prioritize safety over freedom and
others would prioritize freedom over
safety and both of those are defensible
positions so we don't necessarily expect
everyone to agree on them but the fact
that the list of things that society
that a good society would accomplish is
relatively easy to get agreement on it
is very hopeful because it means we can
paint with a broad brush what we are
trying to accomplish with relative ease
and there's another thing that works in
our favor here which is that in a
complex system in a complex system with
an objective right so there are complex
systems like weather in which there is
no objective but in a complex system
with an objective like society
there are automatically diminishing
returns with responsive with respect to
each of the objectives that can be
labeled and what that means is that you
can achieve a large fraction of an
objective but the closer you try to get
to perfection with respect to it the
larger the costs in terms of other
values so what this means is that if we
can agree on the list of things that a
game be world would achieve and we can
agree that we don't want a hundred
percent on any of them but what we want
is the lion's share of all of them we
can have that and you know the folks who
prefer safety over Liberty can probably
have their life biased in that direction
and those who prefer Liberty over safety
could probably have their lives biased
in the direction they prefer and they
wouldn't have to be an important
conflict about those things because
everybody would get the majority of
everything that they were looking for
and with the initial game be community
what were the failure points of that
particular organization I've spoken to a
few people and they've said that there
was a big split around the idea of kind
of personal growth and systems change or
institutions is that is that true it's
not what you saw play out I did see it
play out I'm not sure I agree on what
the question is because maybe I just
simply fall out with the systems folks
but I believe that the spiritual
dimension is important but I believe
that it is something it is an outgrowth
of a system that is actually well enough
architected to free you to explore that
and exploring it in the space of design
is nonsensical it is putting the cart
before the horse as it were so I'm very
much interested in seeing a world that
addresses that problem I'm not so sure
that game B discussions themselves need
to address that problem and in fact I
gave a talk many years ago on what I
called the personal responsibility
vortex
and the personal responsibility vortex
was about the wrongheaded idea that one
fixes the world through behaving in a
personally responsible way that will
then scale up and in fact the exact
opposite is true if you hold people to
live the values that they would like to
see fit civilization then the best
people will be hobbled by their level of
obligation - for example sustainability
and they will have very little impact on
the way the world comes to look and
those who pay no attention to
sustainability will have lots of extra
resource and freedom with which to shape
the world to their objective so if you
want to see the world look a particular
way holding people to that exact
standard in the moment is seems right
but the counterintuitive truth is it's
dead wrong and will be counterproductive
but but you did see that that split play
out in terms of the direction or the the
would you agree that that was the major
split between the two different camps
within game be when it split well I
certainly saw that conflict and I guess
I would say one has to figure out how at
the moment that that split emerges and
it's not the last time it will be seen
in any space that aspires to this sort
of thing it's likely to be seen but at
the point you have those two camps the
obvious thing to do is to divide them
and say look you can't solve the
systemic issue by you know some sort of
personal exploration it doesn't
invalidate personal exploration personal
exploration is wonderful but if you want
to go do that then that's either attacks
on the systems discussion right or it
belongs separated from it so why don't
you do that and you know I'd be
perfectly happy to see people who were
interested in that maybe even primarily
interested in that but also have an
interest in the system's discussion to
come participate in a systems discussion
but the systems discussion is not the
place for that exploration it may be a
place to discuss
how you would make civilization
hospitable to such explorations but as
I've said elsewhere in order to have a
compassionate society you have to do a
dispassionate analysis of the various
problems that prevent it so that you can
address them and so I think this is
counterintuitive to people I know it is
but when you hear people being
dispassionate it is not a failure of
their emotional structure it is a proper
corralling of that structure so it
doesn't get in the road of creating a
system that in the long term Foster's
exactly the thing that those who are
focused on personal growth we would like
to see yeah what do you think was some
of the the reasons you said that it kind
of collapsed or it fell apart can you
could you talk a bit more about what the
tensions were within the community and
why you think that happened in my view I
would say this is not canonical just my
view is there were two fissions that we
are not quite entirely orthogonal with
each other but are different there was
let's call it the institution's or tools
first faction and the change yourself
faction and then there was an overlay of
what I'd call Wu versus anti Wu Wu
meaning belief in the supernatural or
what I would say bullshit right and they
were definitely a faction who especially
I think they were all on the personal
change side who really got into what I
would call wound ooh a jury etc and but
not all the personal change people were
of that sort many of them were you know
personal change in other ways but and
and I think the final threshold which
caused the death throes were a small
group of people started to proclaim or
at least were perceived to be
proclaiming and this may or may not
actually have happened that the the
perception might not have been accurate
or it may been so hazy it's hard to tell
that some form of whoo should become
mandatory and that would be utterly
unacceptable to both the anti Wu and the
institutional faction I would say of the
ant
Wars yo is number one you know what I'm
one of my display and all that mean is
that some form of whoo-whoo mandatory
yeah that you have to accept for
instance that there's a cosmic
consciousness right I go I don't believe
in oh god damn causing the consciousness
to you could prove it right one of my
favorite quotes that I like to use that
I wrote is when I hear the word
metaphysics I reach for my pistol
I am a hardcore scientific realist
I don't believe shit unless there's
evidence right on the other hand I don't
rule things out either I say yeah Nold
yahweh may actually exist they get
incredibly improbable but until someone
can present evidence that yahweh exists
that's independently reproducible I am
NOT going to believe in Yahweh right nor
am I gonna believe in Cosmic
Consciousness Azure and that kind of
worship but can you unpack what that
means that some people wanted that to be
compulsory yeah what did that look like
and who was that I say so again there
was at least they sensed and again maybe
we overreacted that there was a small
number of people who were proposing that
game be should include a metaphysical
statement about reality beyond
scientific realism I guess that's the
way to say it
you know let's say for instance that
there is a cosmic consciousness so why
did staunton six not happen I think the
the decohesion of the community across
all these various lines including people
interested in the party still which
there were still a few those interested
in institution-building those interested
in personal change those interested in
woo metaphysics and and people started
getting mad at each other you know for
promoting their point of view and the
systemd cohered i think it's the best
way to describe it and at that point I
said oh yeah no point in bringing people
together so we can just have a fight and
so it so it never happened when the
initial sort of Stenton meeting stops I
know Jim said that that it was basically
going to spore mode that a lot of the
original people went off and did their
own projects and it seems that though
spores or at least the kind of the meme
of game beers now getting a lot more
attention there's like Facebook grooves
it's got some presence on Twitter it's
sort of growing up one did has that
surprised you at all and to actually
just one is that Supriya make of the the
the kind of the resurgence of interest
in this area well I see it as a result
of a couple of different things and one
of them I had some involvement and I
mentioned game B at some length on Joe
Rogan's podcast and I know that there
was a flurry of interest that came from
that so in one way it can't surprise me
too much because I was sort of hoping to
see it and went about talking about it
publicly now even at the point that I
was talking about it on Joe Rogan's
program there was already a kind of
organic I think slower growing movement
on Facebook and elsewhere
I have been reluctant about
participating in it for various reasons
but nonetheless I'm not surprised that
something has emerged I'm a little bit
startled by the way I hear game be
discussed and I feel like the energy
that one of the things that worked in
our favor in the game be discussion was
the fact that we were nobody to anyone
right this was an invisible discussion
and because it was an invisible
discussion we had the capacity to
explore down different avenues without
worrying so much about what it meant and
now that there is sort of a public
awareness in certain circles about game
B and Stanton and all of these things I
think there's a tremendous danger of the
idea being you know captured would be
the worst way it could fail the more
likely way is it could evolve in some
direction that is counterproductive you
must talk a bit more violence it is very
difficult to distinguish between people
who earnestly believe something and
espouse it because of their earnest
belief and people who discover that
espousing that belief puts them ahead
and it is 100% inevitable that people
who see the game be discussion as an
opportunity will find their way there
and will say the kinds of things that
get people to not along and that that
thing that momentum can take a movement
that is highly generative and can swamp
it with something else and I really
don't have any interest in participating
into something else
the question is we actually faced this
question at the end of the Stanton
meetings which was there was a desire to
increase the size of the discussion
which I think everybody agreed was a
good idea but there was this sort of
rush to bring people in and I tried to
caution at the time that a single error
is very costly so you may bring in ten
generative people there may be
diminishing returns on your generative
people in other words a lot of what they
bring to the table may already be in the
room but one mistake right one bad actor
or one person who is motivated by what I
would call social truth rather than an
analytical truth can cause tremendous
havoc and so I thought we were making an
error in a couple of different ways one
I thought that the idea that the
organization moved from being the
Emancipation party into being game be
that turned out to be an error pretty
clearly game B is not an organization it
should never be an organization and the
Emancipation Party rightly was it made
this one so there should have been a
relationship between those two things
and what I'm getting at is instead of
doing what we did which was decided that
the Emancipation Party was a non-starter
I think 2016 election in the US and what
you saw in Britain with brexit in 2016
tells us that actually there was room
for some sort of an alternative party
and if the Emancipation Party had stuck
it out from 2013 who knows what might
have happened but the Emancipation party
at the point that we decided it was not
the right moment in history for the
Emancipation Party should have become a
sub-project of whatever the organization
was functioning towards a game be
objective that's not what we did we
decided the Emancipation Party was no
more we decided that this was game B
which was an error and then we decided
to increase who was in the room which
took whatever tensions were already
there be they tensions between the
spiritual and the systemic or or
whatever and it made them worse
so one thing I would advise anybody
attempting to build a game be entity is
to figure out how to insulate things
that are functional from things whose
impact you don't yet know so in other
words some capacity to go in reverse or
to change direction or some isolate that
can be preserved if your decision that
you've just made turns out to have been
a mistake and we didn't we didn't do
that we we just simply decided the
organization should grow and that would
have been fatal if nothing else was and
you mentioned coherence as one lesson
that maybe can be learned from it but do
you think the other lessons are
especially now that there's a kind of
resurgence of interest in the whole game
be
space well well what should people take
on board coherence for sure and second
and this would be perhaps controversial
is that institutions do matter and that
neo game be once it decides to get
beyond being a talk shop should build
some early institutions on how to do
things you know a justice system which
we eventually did build and late game be
called the ad hoc justice process and
then when there was a call to build a
formal justice process never got done
but some preliminary institutions but
that are known to be contingent and that
they're not well formed yet and that
they were subject to amendment so it
needs to have an amendment meta process
so I would strongly suggest at some
point that a line be drawn at least a
minimal set of bootstrap institutions
come into existence second third that
the onboarding process be more rigorous
or at least you know the fairly rigorous
in game B but that it be tuned for
coherence rather than X too much
exploration or I title I'll take that
back a balance between coherence and
exploration the game be late-game be was
too much exploration not enough
coherence mmm and you also said earlier
on the there's a danger incoherence yes
I mean what is ultimate coherence a cult
right or a dictatorship so I see that
coherence is hugely important but I
would say absolute coherence ie lack of
coherent pluralism is even worse than no
coherence or yeah like you can argue
whether North Korea is worse than
Anarchy I don't know they both suck
right and that's that you know North
Korea extreme coherence pure anarchy no
coherence and so what you want to be is
somewhere in the middle with a
thoughtful nuanced balance of where you
are and what makes ya make it this is
the coherent core we all agree we
believe this
or if we don't were not part and an
explicit statement that anything that's
not in the core is pluralistic until
they're filled through some
institutional process we may find some
new things we want to add to the core we
also through an institutional process
made once to take some things out of the
core spore mode spore mode refers to
mushrooms you know the the real mushroom
lives underground or in rotten wood etc
then the so called fruiting body is the
thing that we see and that we eat and
typically it grows up and then it fruits
which are typically spores which are
tiny tiny tiny little seeds which often
get blown by the wind a long way and
mushroom spores can often exist for many
many years if the conditions are right
before they sprout and when the
conditions are right then they sprout
and a new mushroom grows so that was the
model I decided to use sort of at the
end of active game B they were going
into sport mode everyone is gonna do are
gonna disperse our spores ie our people
out into the world and they'll continue
to do whatever it is they do and perhaps
in a different time in a different
climate and as the world's changed this
things have been learned some of those
spores will take root again and grow new
mushrooms and so in the last few months
that seems to be happening you want to
tell us what's going on now truthfully I
can't tell you for sure but we've
noticed a tremendous upsurge in interest
in game B in I guess we don't were here
in October so it was certainly happening
in July June July I haven't truthfully
tracked back the traffic I think some of
it were some of the podcasts that had
been done you know Jordan and Daniel
Sherman burger we've been on podcasts I
was on a few podcasts I think my own
interviews of Jordan and Daniel may have
helped but something happened in that
June July timeframe and game B seems to
be you know spreading and groups of
people we don't know or weren't
connected to or doing a really good work
particularly the Twitter game B I was
talking to Jordan about that a couple
days ago and I said we didn't know any
of those people
somehow you know come upon all of our
various works and went and been actively
working them and have created these very
interesting online Google Docs which
point to all kinds of references and
take extracts from podcasts and essays
and things and it's really amazing it's
very game be ish right non hierarchical
Network centric and maybe it's
metastable din last a long time will say
so there's a community on Twitter
there's a community a community with
hashtag game B's probably the easiest
way to find them and there's a very
rapidly growing community on Facebook in
the Facebook group game be and make sure
you answer the three questions dammit if
you apply for membership because you
will not be lied in if you don't answer
the three questions and what do you make
of the this current upsurge did it take
you by surprise or what what what are
you saying
what do you think it well how did it
look to you ah it's a very excellent
question out surprise about any given
time yes right because you know one of
the things we learn from a complexity
systems perspective is the trajectory of
a complex system is exceedingly
difficult to predict however you may be
able to predict some averages across
ensembles of subject Ares and so when we
put game B into spore mode I might have
said there was a 50% chance he to come
back to life someday
right but when I had no clue and the
fact that it seems have come back to
life this summer I would not have
predicted in advance and that's typical
complex system story phase transitions
as we call them are typically
unpredictable and so a phase transition
seems to have occurred and it's now self
generating and probably growing with an
exponential with some exponent greater
than one which means if you wait long
enough it'll conquer the whole world but
what how long that exponent will remain
greater than one I don't know but it's
actually quite interesting and in fact I
like it about it is that it is very game
B it's bottoms up nobody dictating what
game B is people kind of collectively
creating it no as I said earlier I do
believe at some point they need to build
some institutional
structures in there to keep the problem
of the previous problem of decoherence
from occurring hmm and I mean you
mentioned the names Jordan and Daniel
and so a lot of the energy at the moment
is around that particular kind of
conception of game B what do you make of
that yeah I think this fair to say that
the most actual work that has been done
on game B since 2014 has been done by
what I call the San Diego configuration
of the San Diego group which is Jordan
Hall Daniel Sherman burger forest the
hell's his name Forrest Forrest Forrest
Landry and various in sundry other folks
and they've done some very good work
Forrest is on some really interesting
work on how to run organizations without
rigid hierarchies how to go from culture
to operating entities and back again
where does consensus work where do other
forms of things work Daniels done some
great exploration hadn't come to any
answers but he's put some very
significant flags out on what a new
economics might look like Jordans done a
lot of good theoretical work on what
does this all mean from a larger
perspective and so I say they've done it
a really good body of work however
they'll be the first to admit they have
done nothing like the definitive answer
what is game B they've essentially put
out a series of piece parts and partial
you know philosophical perspectives but
there's still a tremendous amount to be
done and I will say they've been
exemplary and not claiming that they
have defying game B they've been very
upfront about we've done our piece other
people have to do theirs now one thing
that I would disagree with them some is
their approach is they seem to be
consciously taking a let's go slow and
keep it somewhat private for now
perspective you know
you know brought forth the the quote
that the perfect the perfect is the
enemy of the good
and I would say our world is a
sufficient need for more good that my
own biases and they are biases I have no
idea if I'm right is to move things into
the world sooner where they're critiqued
by other people and where they're tried
you know and I think that's you know my
own philosophy of game be that it is
very experimental an exploratory we
don't know and trying to trying to can
all the answers in advance is a fool's
errand what time you spent ten years
doing it you're gonna then go out in the
real world and find out eighty percent
of it was wrong to my mind at least
again it's different approach and then
the San Diego crew I'd say let's take a
reasonable rough set of ideas you know
build a Minimum Viable Product launch it
maybe fail tune it relaunch it and to my
mind that's a better way to explore a
vast space that and that is really
difficult to parse in advance and so you
actually engage the world one of the
lessons that I try to teach my children
is that you need to develop a deep
relationship with the idea of
prototyping that prototyping is the way
you learn to accomplish something you do
not have know how to do and the
mythology around the construction of
things does not pay nearly enough
attention to prototyping so if we look
at the United States as a project we
might come to the conclusion that it is
a failed project if we look at it as a
prototype then we can say well this was
actually a wildly successful prototype
that eventually showed what about the
design wasn't quite right it is
definitely time for a 2.0 version of
something what's more it has to be a 2.0
version of something that does not
require the collapse of what is somehow
we have to seamlessly move
from our prototype to something that is
more capable and stable without this one
coming apart that's why I make this
point about competitive superiority and
sweeping across civilization without
having to win power and change the
structures in some sort of more direct
way
I guess one final point I would make is
I think there's a tension that I have
it's been described in many places but I
haven't seen it described with full
breadth anywhere which is that those
things which are the most capable are
always fragile ok to the extent that we
wish to have conversations that can
reach greater heights those
conversations are absolutely vulnerable
to being disrupted by anybody who
doesn't want them to happen right so
high capacity and vulnerability go
together in a way that's not how we
imagined it typically we think that's
something that is highly capable is also
very strong rather than very vulnerable
what we're talking about is a discussion
in which we are able to see what might
be possible for civilization and how it
might be architected to be anti fragile
and evolutionarily stable in the end but
that discussion itself will be fragile
it has to be protected and protected
from all kinds of things that threaten
it which means things like naivete it
has to be protected from bad actors it
has to be protected from people who are
looking to use it as an avenue to propel
themselves somewhere all of these things
threaten it and they all necessitate
that you'd be able to take a
conversation that's functional and
shield it right field it from anything
which challenges it so that it can
wrestle with things and it can make
errors and it can fall down and get back
up again rather than suffer whatever
fate it would suffer if just left to the
the whims of the populace mmm it feels
like a very natural segue into the
intellectual darkweb conversation which
we could also maybe see as a prototype
absolutely because one one last point on
this that I wanted to raise it's
something the references are something
that you and Eric talked about in the
Rubin report where you talked about how
truth cannot survive the encounter with
market forces which I think it's a
really valuable frame to look at the
sort of game a game B conversation
especially because I saw him one of the
in the game B Facebook group someone
said well what is what is game B
journalism and I thought about that for
a while like that's my area of interest
interesting I thought well at its best
journalism is game B in the same way
that academia is game B and so if you
realize that it's like that they have to
be like game B journalism should be
about pew like true truly ethical
information so if you have any kind of
allegation you've got to put it to the
person get their response you're
supposed to get all the views of
everyone before doing your story so it's
so that as a case study journalism and
academia why are they failing is
probably as good a way as any to kind of
look at okay what are what are the what
are the factors that are making game
well a game suppose a game B enterprise
what are the game a factors that are
making them fail so I think another way
to look at this is that there are many
things that exist where we increasingly
only know they're pathological form and
it is the conflation of the pathological
form with the form itself that is so
confusing so the fact that there is
almost no game B journalism means that
we understand journal journalism to be
this malformed arbitrary on truthful
dispenser of information but you're
right
journalism itself would be a game B
enterprise right you report what's true
in spite of its implications for you
personally
the very definition of a game be
enterprise likewise education and
science these are not about discovering
things that are good for you or
profitable these are about discovering
things that are true and teaching people
how to think about them they would
inherently be game B versions medicine I
mean even you know as much as the
Hippocratic oath may be a little bit
antiquated at this point it does reveal
that at some level there was an
understanding about what medicines
purpose was do we really doubt that the
purpose of modern medicine is to make a
profit for those who make the drugs and
dispense the materials and all of the
other enterprises within that scope it's
very purpose has changed and it does a
tremendous amount of harm to people in
the moment because you can't have two
purposes as your top priority so yes
game B should something figure out how
to bring us to such a world we will
discover that many of the forms that
we've seen distorted are really
permutations of something honorable that
has been lost so one of my concerns
about the way the game be conversation
is unfolding is that it is collapsing
all of the conversations that might
ultimately produce their own prototype
into one conversation and I don't see
any way that that can end well we talked
about this a little bit during the stand
meetings I raised the question about
whether or not we were the only
discussion of this kind or whether there
were a hundred such rooms or a thousand
and it was clear to me and I think many
others that it would have been wonderful
had there been many such discussions
because only one of them has to work the
point of a game B is not for us to
produce a world that will work it's for
somebody to accomplish it and in some
ways best possible outcome for any
individual is for somebody else to
figure out how to get us there because
it really takes the pressure off and it
means you
to have the advantages of that wonderful
world on the far side but I think one of
the things that we have learned in that
discussion and then us all fanning out
from it is that there aren't a lot of
such conversations and that there's
actually probably a reason for that
which is that the way we are connected
together today there is a strong
tendency for people who are like-minded
enough to have thought their way down
that road to some degree to coalesce
into one discussion and that tendency to
coalesce into one discussion means that
the chances of multiple variations on
that theme resulting in one of them
surviving and beating the odds is
greatly reduced so I am a little
concerned you know there are lots of
people who are now in this game B space
who are not at the Stanton meetings and
what concerns me is I mean people like
Jamie Weil and Daniel Martin burger is
that instead of us all being in one
conversation wouldn't we be better off
if those were separate nodes and I mean
not saying what we shouldn't be talking
to each other but the idea that it is
all one discussion looking for one
solution just reduces the odds of
success all the more isn't there a
paradox then in that the more we talk
about it the more it becomes one
discussion so isn't talking about it
kind of feeding that trend towards it
being one one conversation you know Eric
and I and Heather and I have a kind of
mode that we go into and we discuss
something that is very uncertain and on
which something important rests and it
involves figuring out how to isolate
your beliefs so that you can discuss
them without them being altered alright
so in other words there's some sort of a
formalization and discussion about all
right I'm gonna lock down what I believe
about this topic you lock down what you
believe about this top
then we're gonna meet and we're gonna
discuss whether or not thus the same
beliefs we turn out to have the same
belief then okay that gives us increased
confidence that there's probably
something true about that belief if we
find out that we're actually in
different places when we meet in the
middle
then we step very carefully because at
least having formalized our belief
before our position moves allows us to
say okay I made a jump right that means
if it turns out that down the road that
jump was counterproductive
I can probably unmake that jump I can
remember what it was like to think that
other thing beforehand whereas the
natural tendency in informal
conversation is for your position to
move as you are persuaded and
unfortunately many people are unduly
persuaded by somebody else's intensity
of belief so it's a sort of a cultivated
skill that you will avoid being
persuaded by the fact that somebody that
you like is very convinced of something
so what I would argue is that we have to
have conversations right I mean those
people that we were discussing are
connected socially they will have
discussions and it is natural for those
discussions to have some overlap with
this territory but maybe there needs to
be some formalization around how to make
sure that the conversations don't
synonymous or average or whatever it is
that they will tend to do so that their
independence from each other can be
utilized you know you know in a
functional Academy this would be the way
different laboratories studying the same
question would function it would be the
way different schools of thought behave
there would be interaction between them
but there would also be enough
insulation that we could sort of track
the development of what happened when
the question of spore mode that Jim
wrought raised whether at the end of the
Stanton meetings the game be entity
dispersed to the wind and the
independent nodes in that discussion
were germinating the ideas
there's some potential truth in that but
I'm concerned that that's not really
what happened and that because the idea
of game be reawakened in the age of
social media and YouTube that what we
have is an idea loosely defined that
because there is a lot of energy around
the idea of living in the better world
that is loosely proposed in that
definition that the conversation is now
developing in a space that not only has
no proper rule set but is also has no
evolutionary history we don't know that
discussions like this are productive
frankly we don't know and I think have
strong reason to believe that we're the
founding fathers to have built the
prototype that is the American
experiment in the social media age that
it would not have worked well so I think
we need to be very careful about what it
means the spore mode is a very loose
description of what happened and what as
the spores germinated and were again in
contact with each other through some
network whose rules we don't understand
whether that doesn't immediacy
immediately challenged the idea that
they were spores and that they might
grow a part into unique plants so what's
your concern with the conversation as it
exists now in social media age well I
have to say I'm a little bit at a
disadvantage talking about the
conversation as it's actually happening
because I have stayed out of it and I've
stayed out of it for some very
intentional reasons and then some other
reasons that were just happenstance the
intentional reason is that I have seen
the power of beliefs persuade people of
fictions and I know this process to be
very difficult to resist
if you were in those conversations day
in and day out so they kind of your
belief system gets chiseled away at just
by virtue of the fact that lots of
people are repeating something that you
just lose the ability to to protect so
I've stayed out of it in part because I
don't think the conversation is
productive enough to justify that hazard
the independence of thought is valuable
enough to be worth staying out and then
of course there's the circumstances that
unfolded around my exit from Evergreen
which made Facebook in particular an
almost impossible place for me to
tolerate so I had been a user of
Facebook not I was never enthusiastic
about it but I had been a user of
Facebook and at the point that Evergreen
came apart I stepped away from it and I
really haven't been able to go back just
by virtue of what sort of discussion it
is so I can't speak to the particulars
of the discussion but I can say in
general a large freeform discussion in
which people gather as a result of the
appeal of some concept those discussions
are not likely to be highly fruitful
because the the curation that has to go
on at the door in order to create one of
these highly generative but fragile
conversations needs to be better than
that but if we define freedom in terms
of how much Liberty you actually have
that you can act upon right that you can
engage in the real world then we will
discover a couple of things one is that
if you have achieved great deals of
realized freedom that you have probably
achieved all of the other goals and
balanced them in a way that is desirable
what what are your biggest takeaways
when you look back on that time and you
sort of look at where we're at now what
are your biggest takeaway is what do you
look back and think I think we were damn
prescient that things would get worse
which they certainly have we were
a little prescient about the fact that
we were rapidly approaching the limits
of the ecosystem I think that was one
area where we were not as prescient as
we could have been and so there that's
that's interesting I think that we it
highlights to me the tremendous failure
of organizational design and dynamics
above all else and that's why I think
the forest land rework may well be
critical to neo game B succeeding or
failing or if not his than somebody
else's but I should say this is very
important that any high dimensional
complex systems
you cannot say in advance whether X will
work you've got to take it
experimentalist perspective you've got
to try it and I know he believes this as
well he wants to try it on two groups
relatively small than larger groups etc
so all these tools and techniques the
piece parts for which we will build game
B have got to all be taken from an
empirical experimental perspective tried
and see if they work and if they do then
that we vet that they are suitable for
at least the early stages a game B maybe
we turns out they're only good for up to
2,500 people and you have to rethink it
so I would strongly suggest to those
interested in game B stay light on your
feet
don't make over strong commitments to
anything when things stop working pitch
them and try something else
mmm yeah I think that's kind of my last
question is what advice would you have
for people just discovering this kind of
space or the Neo game B where where did
it go from here that's a excellent
question you know there's I think
probably a couple of different
directions one is because of the nature
of the foundations of game B it will be
a talking shop forever there will be
people bloviating about various and
sundry game B related topics both
allegedly practical and others purely
theoretical forever that's it's built
into the DNA and if you want to blow v8
you can find fellow bloviator that to to
the cows come home on the other hand I
wouldn't suggest it's time for more
doers to show up and particularly on
Twitter
maybe there are people now pounding the
table let's do something let's do
something and for people who like to do
things I'd suggest find the other doers
and go do something and realize it ain't
gonna be perfect the first time out of
the out of the suit and even in this
experiment with the peace parts you
don't like the you don't like public
schools which is why the I think
relatively consistent beliefs in the
game be community you know then build a
charter school in your community and use
your ideas see how they work and make
sure it see if there and make sure
they're informed with game B ethos and
if it works report back you know that's
a big key part do experiments report
back and report your failures and your
successes yeah what I mean you just gave
the example of education here what are
the other sort of solid ideas solid
concrete ideas that came out of this or
things that needed to be solved whether
they were actually frankly did we do
anything useful I know but did we talk
about a lot about them yes well how to
run and not a build and run an
organization we identified that as
absolutely critical
education health and distinguishing that
from health care right but we in the
United States way too much talk about
health care when really what we want is
health and that includes eating good
food exercising plenty you know not
being annoyed by being overstressed by
your damn smartphone and lots and lots
of things so taking a holistic
perspective on health was clearly a
theme and we're somewhat related to
health was it was always a strong
interest in food and clean food local
food you know food that could be that
you know that was not overly refined but
was interesting and good and probably
built you know created by people you
already knew housing was a big one that
said there was a for a and trying to
understand Co housing and we had a
person Lidia Lorenson who actually had
been the manager a couple of co housing
projects he was a huge and wonderful
resource but that stimulated a big
conversation the sharing economy we
talked a lot about the sharing economy
in 2013 a little bit
they're things like to libraries and
perhaps joint ownership of cars and
things of that ilk again to make
people's lives less economically
intensive and less environmentally
intensive does everybody need a car fuck
now you just need n cars across n people
M people for X missions right and it's
probably a shitload less than the
typical American has who has you know
2.7 cars and probably needs a 1.1 on
average maybe less than that can you
consider how many hey you know you drive
your car to work and it sits there 8-day
eight hours that's crazy right
so we talked about a lot of these kinds
of things one that's arisen in neo game
B and in the next episode of the gym rut
show Jordan and I go over all fairly
long list of these things one of them is
parenting I think there's been a lot of
interest in you know preschool age
children how do the parents and the
children interact correctly what is the
right kind of home life for children you
know how do we how do we help make sure
that game B children are well-balanced
joyful productive non neurotic etc so I
think that's an area there's a lot of
interest in right now again the other
one that's new since view game be 100 we
had kind of a hazy vision of it is
what's called sense making this is a key
interest of a community came right
before neo game be called rally point
alpha which you can check out on
Facebook the rally point alpha group
which was triggered by a essay by Jordan
and has tried to dedicate itself to
understand how networked individuals can
make sense of the world in a powerful
fashion are we currently doing it now
and there needs to be more things
including perhaps better tools but sense
making is certainly
category of great interest in the Neo
game B world and clubbing we share with
the all the way back to the Emancipation
Party is a strong interest in rethinking
economics the monetary system banking
investment rival risks versus non rival
worse economics those have been themes
consistent all the way through and I
would particularly point people to
Daniel SH Martin burgers essays that are
pointing the way towards what a new
economics might be and so I'll just
reiterate one more time that for game B
to be real at some point it has to make
the transition from talk to action and
we can talk to the cows come home but
it's action that really changes the
world
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom Jim a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]